[Music]
okay so welcome to episode four of our
inventory system tutorial series where
we left it off is if we go um down here
and then we hit play you can see that
we've got our empty inventory slots here
and as we go over the slots we pick up
uh
these two sort of different items some
of them can stack
the green one can't there was only one
of them anyway you can see that they've
just got these ugly white sprites in
them in a minute so let's get some
sprites downloaded so we can actually
start to see stuff uh appear in our
inventory this um there's this cozy farm
asset pack which is a really nice pack
includes a lot if you pay for it and but
you can get it for free there is a free
version so if you click no thanks just
take me to the downloads you get this
free version dot zip and just hit
download on that what you'll get is
you'll get this uh png with just some
basic tiles so if we just drag this into
our project so i'm gonna go over to our
assets folder i'm gonna right click
create folder and let's type graphics
so i'm just going to drag this png in
and we're going to need to do a couple
of things first so the first thing is we
want to mark this as a sprite we want to
set the sprite mode to multiple
uh filter mode we want to change to no
filter point
compression we can choose none and then
we need to hit apply this is one image
with lots of sprites on it so we need to
slice the image and
[Music]
up into its multiple parts and to do
that we need to access the sprite editor
if you've just started a normal 3d
project in unity you won't have the 2d
sprite package installed and you'll get
this error so we just need to go up to
window
package manager go over to unity
registry and then choose 2d sprite and
just install the 2d sprite package so
with that installed we can just close
out the package manager select our image
again choose the sprite editor
and then we just um
for what we need we just want these two
sprites here the potato and the
tomato so if we hit slice and then just
choose automatic it's going to slice up
all of the um
[Music]
it's going to try and detect
things to slice so where you've got a
png it'll do a cut around them it's not
worked perfectly for this whole image
but we just wanted these two sprites so
we've got those sprites there so we can
we've hit slice so we can just click
apply
and now if we expand this out you can
see that what it's done is it's you know
sliced them up
kind of wrongly
but
here's our potato and our tomato so now
if we go back over to our scriptable
objects
and go to test item and i'm just going
to rename this to tomato
i'm gonna select tomato and let's type
tomato there
this is a tomato
i'm gonna have a maximum stack size of
five still and i'm just gonna choose the
tomato from
for the icon
and then i'm just going to do this and i
will say
potato
and i say potato and tomato because i
won't say tamar tomato
so with potato we will choose the icon
and we'll pick the potato icon
and we'll say the display name is potato
and
this is a potato
so now we've got our two test items so
now with our test item one this is the
tomato which is quite it's worked out
well because it's red so i'm just going
to rename
this to tomato i'm just going to delete
the other ones so i'd have to rename all
of them
for the test item three
let's call it potato and i might
actually just change the color of it
to be more potato color
because why not so
rename this to
potato
let's pick more of a potato cooler which
kind of
that color i suppose
now we've got a potato and a tomato the
potato
won't stack it's got a maximum stack
size of one so it's not going to carry
on stacking so now we've got our tomato
and our potato we can just um i'm just
going to select them both and drag them
down to the bottom i'm just going to
duplicate them a couple of times so i'm
going to get the move tool ctrl d let's
duplicate them
ctrl d duplicate them again
duplicate them some more
i'm going to get all of the tomatoes
because these stack we want a few of
these
so we can actually pick them up
and actually why don't i do that with
the potatoes as well just so we've got
multiple things to work with
so if we now hit uh actually let's
select all of these
and just bring them down to the bottom
and then i'm going to
group all of these together
under a
object just called items
just keep the
hierarchy organized so let's drag that
in we can just collapse that so we've
got our items here now and you'll see
that as we go over them
now the icons that we've set should
appear in our inventory when we pick
them up so there's our tomato you can
see that we've got
five tomatoes are stacking
and then the potatoes don't stack and
they fill up our inventory now our
inventory is full we can't pick up any
more
and i don't like the
font here being black so let's just go
over to the canvas uh play hopper
get one of our slots and just open it up
and i'm going to change the item count
to
white
and we can maybe give it uh
an outline so just check the outline
just so we can definitely see it over
the images
there you go we've got five
five tomatoes so we just need to um
choose our prefab and then hit apply all
and that'll apply it to the rest of them
so as we hit play
you see that when we've got more than
one item
it comes up
and shows us the item in our inventory
so now the next thing we want to do is
we want to start be able to click on the
items and actually do stuff because at
the moment nothing happens when we click
on the items we want to be able to pick
it up
and
manipulate this mouse item to show
the item that we've got selected and we
want to remove it from the slot and do
lots of interesting stuff of it just to
show how that's going to work
we're going to run over these items and
then we can pick them up move them
around and place them down so this is
what we're going to be working towards
in this episode
moving them between the slots
so let's go back over to our scripts
folder and we've got our ui scripts and
i believe we need to open up the
inventory display script so here's our
inventory display clicked uh
here's our inventory display script
in the last episode um
you know we set this up and we set up
the static inventory display as a
that inherits from this class
but all displays are going to
have slots that can be clicked and at
the minute it just prints out slot
clicked when we click it what we want to
do is we want to start picking up items
and moving them around so let's just get
to work on that straight away so first
thing we want to do
we're going to need a few different
checks because there's a lot of
different things that need to happen
based on
a few different contexts so
if the clicked slot has an item
and the mouse doesn't have an item
then we will need to pick up the item
because there's nothing currently on the
mouse
we also need to account for if we if the
clicked uh slot doesn't have an item
but the mouse does have an item
then we need to place the mouse item
apply place mouse item into the mount uh
the empty slot
we also want to check to see whether
both slots have an item
and if they do
we need to decide what we want to do
there
for example are both items the same if
so
uh we want to combine the stacks if we
can so if we've got you know three
tomatoes on our inventory barn we're
holding four from a different slot can
we combine them
and if they're um
if different
items then we want to swap them
then swap the items
and actually this one has a bit of an
extra step we want to see the um is the
slot
plus as this plot is the slot stack size
plus the mouse
stack
size
greater than um
the slots maximum stack size that it can
take
if so we need to account for that um so
we need to if so uh take
from mouse so we need to take
so if the maximum stack size for
tomatoes is five
and we're currently we've currently got
three in the stack but we've got four in
our mouse
then when we click on the item we're
gonna take two from the mouse to fill
the stack and then we're gonna leave
three
two on the mouse
all right bad math
i'll just i'll just show what i mean
here so if we've got um
[Music]
you know so these hearts they stack to a
maximum of five we've got three in this
stack
if i split this and let's just get
four
so
this three it can only go up to five
but i've got four on my mouse if i click
here
it's going to fill this stack
with two because three plus two is five
so it's going to take two from the four
that i'm currently holding so as i click
i've now got two left on the mouse that
stacks full
and when it is if
we're also accounting for if this
stack's full and we're trying to place
this on top of it it's just gonna swap
them
i'll just swap them over
so that's what we're kind of building up
towards as well
and i'm not sure if we'll get there in
this episode um but we also need to
check if the player
is holding shift
okay
and if they are
we want to split the stack so we want to
separate the stack into two different
stacks we want to leave some in this
slot and put some onto the mouse so
there's quite a lot to get through here
a lot of functionality to build uh we'll
try and do it in one episode we'll see
how we get on
the first thing we'll tackle is this if
the click slot has an item and the mouse
doesn't let's pick it up let's put it
onto the mouse so if we
make some room here so this slot clicks
when we click on the button that's
attached to the slot it's going to call
it's going to reach up to the parent
display
we look at the inventory slot ui
we've got onslot clicked which we've
added as a listener to the buttons on
click event
and it's going to reach up to the parent
display and it's going to say
called slot clicked and it's going to
pass in itself so we know which slot
exactly was clicked
so here we can say if
this clicked slot
uh and just
so we know exactly what's going on i'm
going to rename this to clicked ui
slot
so if clicked ui slot
dot inventory assigned inventory slot
dot data
item data is not equal to null
so
if
the clicked ui slot has an item in it so
it's not null
and the mouse inventory item dot uh
inventory slot so why is that not
working why can't i get that
i hope because i've not actually added
an inventory slot to the mouse so let's
go back
to the mouse we just need to add an
inventory slot to the mouse
so we can do a public
uh inventory
slot
called inventory slot
so we're going to be coming back to this
in a second so i'm just going to move
them i'm just going to close all these
other ones that we don't need so
let's go back to our inventory display
class so um
we've got click slots uh item data and
then mouse
inventoryitem.inventoryslot.itemdata
is not equal
to null
is equal to null so if the um
[Music]
slot has an item in it and the mouse
doesn't
then we can pick up the item and assign
it to the mouse so it'll be in here that
we split the stack if the holding uh the
shift key
so that's if that
but and then we'll do an else but for
now let's just do mouse inventory item
data dot and then we're gonna need to
make a
function on our mouse inventory item
called update mouse slot
and then we're just gonna pass in the
clicked ui slots assigned inventory slot
and then we're going to call click ui
slot
clear slot because there won't be an
item in that slot anymore because we'll
have picked it up so let's go make this
function so it's update mouse slot i'm
just going to copy it so we know it's
called exactly what we want it to be
called
and i'm going to make a public
void and then paste our update mouse
slot and this is going to take in an
inventory slot and it's going to be
called
just in
slot
so here we're gonna um
take our inventory slot and just to
match this up with the clicked ui slot
i'm gonna right click and i'm just let's
rename this to assigned inventory slot
so it matches
just so it matches this so we know kind
of what we're working
with
and so assigned inventory slot dot
assign item
in slot
which is another function we need to
make on our inventory slot
and i'm just going to call this in slot
and we'll do that in a second and so the
next thing we want to do is we want to
set our item sprite dot sprite equal to
the inventory slot
dot item data dot icon
so the item that's in the slot that
we're putting on to our mouse we need to
set our mouse's sprite to the icon
we want to set the um
itemcount.txt equal to the inventory
slot dot stack size
dot to string
and we need to set the item sprite dot
color equal to color dot white so it
becomes visible again
so obviously we we set it to clear
initially
so now we need to make um this assign
item on our inventory slot class let's
go over there here we can say
public void assign
item and we can pass in inventory slot
in slot
and we can just say here
[Music]
the
item data that we're currently that's
currently on this slot
is equal to the item data that we were
picking up
so the inventory slots
item data
so if this inventory slot has some item
data in it and we're trying to add more
of that item to it
then we can just call add to stack and
pass in the inventory slot
dot stack size so this is going to
combine the items
and we can say else
item data is equal to the inventory slot
data that we're passing in so in select
our item data
we're going to set our sax die stack
size back to zero
and then we're going to add the
inventory slot dot stack size
to that so this is going to completely
override the item that was in the slot
if they're different so we're basically
swapping them
well we're not swapping them we're
completely overriding it if the mouse's
um
assigned inventory slot had
a potato on it and we passed in a tomato
an inventory slot with a tomato on it
we're gonna
assign the tomato to the assigned
inventory slot of the mouse so hopefully
that all makes sense let's go back over
to our inventory display class but if
we've done this
then we can just return because we don't
we won't need to check any of the other
stuff because we've already accounted
for what we're doing here so let's just
hit save and go back over to unity oh if
we hit play and we walk over our
tomatoes and we click the slot so i'm
going to set it on our mouse inventory
slot item which doesn't follow our mouse
which will fix that
i'm also going to do what what i did
with the text down here as well i'm just
going to set the mouse slot text to
white
with a slight outline
so now when we hit play pick up an item
so we've got five tomatoes on our mouse
slot so let's let it actually follow the
mouse around now
so to do that we go over to our
mouse item data and because this is a
mono behavior it can get a update
function so we can do void update
and what we want to do here we want to
say if our
assigned inventory slot dot item data is
not equal to null
so remember this is the way we check
whether the mouse has an item actually
on it
so if that's not equal to null
then we want to say transform.position
is equal to mouse we need to be using
unity engine dot input system for this
so using unity engine.input system
we want to say mouse dot current
dot position
dot read
value
so if we have an item set the items
object position to the mouse's current
position so it'll follow the mouse
around and we can go further here to
actually delete the item so if we click
outside of the inventory we can
delete an item so to do that uh we can
get this function here which i found on
i think it was stack overflow which to
use this we need to be using
unityengine.event systems
and we say point our event data event
data current position equals new pointer
event data event system.current we're
going to get the event date as position
and set that equal to the mouse's
position and we're doing a raycast and
this will uh return a list of items that
it hits and it'll hit ui elements it
won't hit stuff in the game world so if
that list is greater than zero then
we've obviously hit ui so it'd return
true
if it doesn't hit any ui it'd be false
so we can say under here if the mouse
dot
current dot left button dot was pressed
this frame
and
we're not
uh is pointer over ui object so we're
not currently hovering over an object
then we can say clear
slot
which is a function we just need to make
down here we can say private void and on
public void because we'll need this
later on so public void clear slot
and this is going to get our assigned
inventory slot and call clear slot
on that so we're going to empty out the
inventory slot
and then we need to reset our
itemcount.txt
to
uh display nothing we want to set the
item
sprite.color
equal to color dot clear
and we can actually just null out the
item spray so item sprite dot sprite is
equal to null as well
so now we go back to our
mouse object
and we hit play
you see that if we pick up an item it
will now follow
the uh mouse and you might not want it
directly under the mouse you might want
it slightly offset so we can do that
so we can do that easily so if we hit 2d
and look at our mouse so the mouse
object is sort of anchored here and
it'll this position in the center will
be what follows the mouse
so we just want to offset the image
uh by
and then we can do
negative 50. so the left corner is now
at the pivot
and then we can just drag the text into
place so if we go to item count and drag
this down
and one thing you'll notice is that it
it was behind the ui
when we click it it goes behind the ui
what we want is we want to get our mouse
object and just drag that to it it needs
to be at the bottom of the canvas which
will draw it on top of everything else
we can hit play and you'll see that it
appears on top of the ui now one thing
you'll notice is if we pick it up it
doesn't actually fully work when we
click to delete the item unless we get
away from the mouse quite quickly
the reason for that is that we need to
make the mouse image
and not be a raycast target otherwise
when we click will always be over a ui
element
because it's following the mouse round
obviously and under the item count text
as well we can come to raycast target
and let's just uncheck that so now when
we go back and hit play
and we pick up an item you see that we
pick it up and we can click off our ui
and it'll delete the item and that slot
is now
empty it's not just the kind of
representation of the slot that the
actual inventory slot has been
uh emptied as well so we can pick up our
tomato
it's out of the slot because it's now on
the mouse and we click and it's gone
there's nothing on the mouse and there's
nothing uh in the hotbar and we could
pick it up if i got the potato on the
mouse delete that so that's gone out of
the game
and we can carry on picking stuff up
so now we could pick up items and we
could delete them but now we need to
pick them up and place them back in slot
so we can move them between our
inventory slots and or keep stuff
organized
so let's go and work on that done that
that's all working so let's go back over
to our inventory display
so we've we've achieved this
let's just go up
okay so let's have a look so the next
thing is the click slot doesn't have an
item but the mouse does so let's place
the mouse item into the empty slots
let's move them around so here we're
basically doing this
but in reverse we're doing the kind of
flip of that so
let's make a new if statement so we can
say if
and let's just bring this up so we know
what we're working on
so if
the uh clicked ui slot
dot assigned inventory slot dot item
data
is uh
equal to null so
the click slot doesn't have an item in
it
and the
mouse inventory item dot
assigned inventory slot dot item data is
not equal to null
so the mouse does have an item let's
place the mouse item into the empty slot
in the same way that we do um
here so here we just need to say click
slot ui
dot assigned inventory slot and then
here we need to assign
the item directly
so we can say mouse inventory item dot
assigned inventory slot dot item data so
after that we need to call clicked ui
slot dot update ui slots we've put a new
item in it so let's just refresh it now
we could put it um you know in this one
and pass in the slot but this is also
called when we pick up an item from the
ground and if we reassign the item when
we pick it up it causes some weird
issues and it adds multiple to it for
some reason um i'm not 100 sure why that
bug was occurring
but
so this is the way around it though you
just assign the item directly and then
you just refresh the slot and then we
need to do what we're doing here but for
the mouse item so we just need to say
mouse inventory item
dot
clear slot
so if we go back over to
unity
let's just hit play
so as we go over we can have pick up
items we can pick them up on our mouse
and we can delete them
and carry on picking up items it'll fill
up the stack when we pick them up and
then it started
a new stack once that stack was full and
we could pick up the items move them and
drop them into the different slots now
if we look at our player on our
inventory we're actually moving them
and
we're actually moving the slots to their
corresponding slot here so we can move
it and put it into the second slot we
can put it into the last slot
see this is kind of working as we
intended now so we can pick up
these potatoes and we can place them in
this slot
and you see that if we pick up the
potato and try and place it somewhere
else nothing happens it has to go kind
of into a blank slot so the next thing
we need to work on is swapping slots and
splitting stacks and we will do that in
the next video and i think that will be
enough for this video so we'll do that
next time um so in the next video we'll
finish up our uh thing here so we'll
we'll swap the items and we'll uh set up
stack splitting as well and we can and
we'll also set up so we'll be able to
combine the stacks once we split them as
well because it's kind of using the
similar sort of functionality so
that's it for this video uh if you're
watching this as they go live as always
the full series is over on
the full series is up on my patreon
already and that's patreon.com forward
slash dan pass
if you've struggled with anything in the
video or need some help or something's
not quite working either leave a comment
below or better yet come join the
discord server an invite for that is in
the description of this video and either
me or maybe someone else would be able
to help you it's probably a quicker way
of getting
a response than here on youtube time
thanks for watching and i'll see you in
the next one bye
you